Okay. בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ו. vav. We're
actually ahead, and we pick up at the bottom of
ו עמוד א vav amud aleph
where it says
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, about eight lines from the bottom. Three, four,
five, eight lines from the bottom at the end of the line
אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. Just to review what we have said until
now is we're looking at the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel
and בית שמאי Beit Shammai about whether which it costs more, which
excuse me has a higher minimum: the עולת ראיה Olat Re'iyah or
the שלמי חגיגה, Shalmei Chagigah, two things that you're obligated to bring
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And בית שמאי Beit Shammai says there's
a minimum of two coins of silver for the עולת ראיה, Olat
Re'iyah, a higher minimum than the חגיגה Chagigah which is one מעה,
ma'ah, and בית הלל Beit Hillel says the reverse. So together they
both have you spending three כסף, kesef, but the interesting logic of
the argument: on the one hand the גמרא Gmara says what I
feel is at the core of other debates of בית הלל Beit
Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, not just משניות mishnayot of מיקל
meikeil or מחמיר, machmir, but that בית שמאי Beit Shammai wants to
give more money spent on the עולה Olah which is all to
God, and בית הלל Beit Hillel wants to give more money spent
on the שלמים Shlamim which you do together with God. So question
of how much does the human being factor in in the equation
in terms of thinking about religious matters seems to certainly be at
what's at the core of that debate. But then the גמרא Gmara
talks about more technical issues in terms of what can serve as
a model for this. And one of the proofs for בית הלל
Beit Hillel that שלמים, Shlamim, the חגיגה Chagigah which is a שלמים,
Shlamim, should get more weight is the fact that you had a
שלמים Shlamim before מתן תורה. Matan Torah. Looking at the verses at
the end of משפטים Mishpatim which חז"ל Chazal understand to have taken
place before מתן תורה, Matan Torah, which says that when משה Moshe
writes down the ספר הברית Sefer Habrit and he sends the youth
of the young men of Israel, נערי בני ישראל, na'arei b'nei Yisrael,
and it says ויזבחו עולות ויזבחו זבחים שלמים לה' פרים. vayizbachu olot
vayizbachu zvachim shlamim l'Hashem parim.
So it says they brought עולות olot and they brought שלמים. shlamim.
So בית הלל Beit Hillel says, look, they had שלמים Shlamim before
מתן תורה Matan Torah and not עולה. Olah. Of course they also
had עולה, Olah, which is what בית שמאי Beit Shammai responds. And
the גמרא Gmara says that what they're really debating is whether those
עולות olot were your standard עולת ראיה Olat Re'iyah or not, if
it was your standard עולת תמיד Olat Tamid or not. And therefore
if it were, it's not relevant because we're looking for a model
of a personal קרבן. korban. So בית הלל Beit Hillel says we
have a model of a personal שלמים Shlamim beforehand, although it's also
quite fascinating because משה Moshe here is appointing people to bring these
קרבנות. korbanot. One gets the sense it's קרבנות korbanot on behalf of
the community, but nevertheless, anyway we don't have a model for what
type of a קרבן korban that would be. So בית הלל Beit
Hillel says the עולה Olah is an עולת תמיד, Olat Tamid, it's
not relevant. The personal קרבן korban is a שלמים. Shlamim. And בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says it is both an עולה Olah and a
שלמים Shlamim that are private and therefore there's no greater weight to
the שלמים. Shlamim. What's also interesting is that the גמרא Gmara frames
it as an עולת ראיה Olat Re'iyah and a שלמי חגיגה. Shalmei
Chagigah. So רש"י Rashi says ראיה Re'iyah we can understand, it's in
the experience of having this vision of God which the תורה Torah
spells out. שלמי חגיגה Shalmei Chagigah less obvious, except of course as
Michael pointed out the other day, it was שבועות, Shavuos, but okay.
So anyway but that is interesting.
Yes,
the אבות avot brought קרבנות korbanot and sometimes they will actually cite
actions of the אבות.
avot. Yeah, it is
true, and an excellent point. And you know the קרבנות korbanot that
we generally find that are explicit actually pre-מתן תורה Matan Torah are
עולות, olot, right? נח Noach brings an עולה Olah and so on.
So it is interesting that we have somehow we have made those
issues moot. It's not saying why, but somehow it's simplified. We're going
to look at it only from the time period of בני ישראל,
B'nei Yisrael, but we're going to give special weight to what happened
before מתן תורה. Matan Torah. It's a very
strange, and why all of a sudden is what's before מתן תורה
Matan Torah give it more weight? Usually what's before מתן תורה Matan
Torah is irrelevant. So it's a very strange argument. But anyway, let's
now pick up
about
six lines, eight lines from the bottom. אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. Says
אביי, Abaye, בית שמאי ורבי אליעזר ורבי ישמעאל כולהו סבירא להו עולה
שהקריבו ישראל במדבר עולת ראיה הוה. Beit Shammai v'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Yishmael
kulhu svira lehu olah shehikrivu Yisrael bamidbar olat re'iyah hava.
So now we are going to sort of broaden this debate. You
know, this key question about what was that עולה Olah that we
hear at the end, together with the שלמים Shlamim that we hear
about at the end of משפטים. Mishpatim. So he says it wasn't
only בית שמאי Beit Shammai that holds it was an עולת ראיה,
Olat Re'iyah, it was בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, a position of רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and a position of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. They
all hold it was an עולת ראיה. Olat Re'iyah. ובית הלל ורבי
עקיבא ורבי יוסי הגלילי, U'Beit Hillel v'Rabbi Akiva v'Rabbi Yose HaGlili, and
on the other hand you have three opinions that hold בית הלל,
Beit Hillel, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, and רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose
HaGlili, דכולהו סבירא להו עולה שהקריבו ישראל במדבר עולת תמיד הוה. d'kulhu
svira lehu olah shehikrivu Yisrael bamidbar olat tamid hava. That they all
hold that it was the עולת תמיד, Olat Tamid, it was not
a personal עולה, Olah, it was not an עולת ראיה. Olat Re'iyah.
Now
let's see how he's going to do because he's basically going to
line up two other Tannaitic debates with this debate of בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So בית שמאי הא דאמרן,
Beit Shammai ha d'amran, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai we've already said.
That's why they feel that you can't give more weight to the
שלמים Shlamim because it was also a private עולה Olah that was
being brought, an עולת ראיה. Olat Re'iyah. רבי ישמעאל הא דתניא, Rabbi
Yishmael ha d'tanya, where is רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? דתניא, d'tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא. Baraita. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael אומר *Rabbi Yishmael
omer*: כללות נאמרו בסיני *Klallos nemru b'Sinai* this is a very famous
debate about how the תורה Torah, *Torah* was given ופרטות באהל מועד
*u'pratos b'Ohel Moed*. At הר סיני Har Sinai *Har Sinai*, you know,
if you read the stuff that was given in יתרו *Yisro*, even
includes some of the stuff that's given in משפטים Mishpatim. *Mishpatim*,
but you don't have you don't have the תורה Torah *Torah* spelled
out in full detail. You have some broad statements, particularly if you
limit yourself to יתרו *Yisro*. But anyway, but then afterwards, after the
הקמת המשכן *Hakamas HaMishkan*, you know, then the תורה Torah *Torah* in
the next three books, you know, a lot more is spelled out.
So the general principles were said at הר סיני Har Sinai. *Har
Sinai*, but all the details were spelled out in the late afterwards
in אהל מועד Ohel Moed. *Ohel Moed*, you know, in the rest
of the four years when God, you know, God says, you know,
ונועדתי לך שם *V'no'aditi lecha sham*, you know, and I'll encounter you
there in the אהל מועד Ohel Moed *Ohel Moed*, and you know,
ודברתי אתך מעל הכפרת *V'dibarti itcha me'al hakapores*, I'll speak to you
משה Moshe *Moshe*. So there was a continued revelation afterwards that occurred
after הר סיני Har Sinai. *Har Sinai*, which spelled out all the
details. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר *Rabbi Akiva omer* says no. כללות
ופרטות נאמרו בסיני klalot upratot ne'emru beSinai, *Klallos u'pratos nemru b'Sinai*, the
broad principles and the details were all given at הר סיני Har
Sinai. *Har Sinai*, ונשנו באהל מועד *v'nishnu b'Ohel Moed*, and they were
repeated in אהל מועד Ohel Moed *Ohel Moed*, ונשתלשו בערבות מואב *v'shulshu
b'Arvos Moav*, and were said a third time in ערבות מואב *Arvos
Moav*. That's a good time, why did you need to repeat them?
I mean, why משה *Moshe* needed to repeat is one thing, he
needed to remind בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael*. Why God needed
to repeat them is actually a good question, I don't know. I'm
so used to this debate, I didn't stop to think about that.
I mean, everything needs חזרה *chazarah*, you know, maybe, I don't know,
it's a good point, because if you wanted to say something like
he spelled out the nuances to משה *Moshe*, so that's more פרטות
*pratos*. So maybe it's a question of the degree of פרטות *pratos*.
It is a very good question. Also it's interesting, given in general
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, you know, because רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
is
the one that normally represents I mean, I actually find this quite
a fascinating debate because I think Heschel talks about it in his
תורה Torah מן השמים *Torah Min HaShamayim*, sort of a three-volume work.
But on the face of it, this seems to be the reverse
of what you generally expect from them because, you know, because
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* holds that you can like דרשן
*darshan* things from every tiny little like קוצו של יוד *kutzos shel
yud*, every little extra letter, every little tittle and dot, you know,
is a basis for
extrapolating the details of the law. But okay, that's extrapolating, but ultimately
it's the human being, right, the whole point to רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* was sort of the human creativity coming encountering the
divine text and having the license to therefore interpret and extrapolate, you
know, whereas רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael. *Rabbi Yishmael* was much more sort
of says you can't go ahead and make all these דרשות *drashos*
on every little thing, דברה תורה Torah כלשון בני אדם *dibra Torah
kilshon bnei adam*, and was much more sort of linked to the
פשט pshat *pshat* of the פסוקים psukim *psukim*.
So if for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva*, you don't need
the פרטות *pratos* to be given at הר סיני Har Sinai *Har
Sinai*, you know, because the text is given for extrapolation, meaning for
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* in general the whole idea of
the פרטות *pratos* being given, you know, there's more of a sense
of the human being having license to derive the פרטות *pratos*, the
details. So I'm not exactly sure how to link this with their
general different type of orientation around these issues.
Yeah, I don't know. But you wanted to say something, Charlie?
Oh, well, ערבות מואב *Arvos Moav*, there was nobody left from at
least among I understand ערבות מואב *Arvos Moav*.
Yeah, no, that's different. ערבות מואב *Arvos Moav* is different. But anyway,
but yeah, it's interesting that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says
like again, you know, all of the פרטים pratim *pratim* because רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* in general is the one that feels
like he only needs a tiny hint and then he can sort
of, unless that's what he means by the פרטים pratim *pratim*. The
fact that all these tiny little hints were there, that's what it
means to give the פרטים pratim *pratim*, and then we're there to
derive them. Whereas רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* basically feels that
no, you know, if you want those details there, they have to
be spelled out, and they weren't spelled out until אהל מועד *Ohel
Moed*. That's probably what it means. Am I being clear about that
at all? You know, so even if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's *Rabbi
Akiva* derives the things from the little hints, so that's what he
means for him therefore that the details are given, that those tiny
little extra letters are given, and that's the giving of the details,
and then we'll figure the rest out. So that's what it means
to give the details, and that was already given at הר סיני
Har Sinai? *Har Sinai*. Whereas according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi
Yishmael*, to give the details means to actually tell me what those
details are. So for him, that didn't happen until אהל מועד *Ohel
Moed*. That's probably how to explain that. Okay, so anyway, that's the
debate. Now how is that relevant? So therefore, ואי סלקא דעתך *v'isaka
daitecha*, let's spell it out. ואי סלקא דעתך *v'isaka daitecha*, if you
hold עולה olah שהקריבו ישראל במדבר עולת תמיד olat tamid הוה *Ola
she'hikrivu Yisrael b'midbar olas tamid hava*, that if the עולה olah? *Ola*
was the תמיד tamid *tamid*, so the point is that the details
of how to bring an עולה olah *Ola* are not spelled out
until ויקרא Vayikra, *Vayikra*, right? So then that means that the עולה
olah, *Ola* that they were bringing, the עולת תמיד olat tamid *olas
tamid* that they were bringing, according
to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* that says the details weren't
given yet, so they were bringing it without doing it exactly the
right way. מי איכא מידי דמעיקרא לא בהפשט וניתוח *mi ka midi
d'me'ikara lo b'hefshet v'nituach*, could there be something that when it was
originally brought, it did not follow all the details, it was not
flayed and dismembered, which is what the תורה Torah, *Torah* says to
do by an עולה olah *Ola*? ובסוף בא בהפשט וניתוח *u'basof ba
b'hefshet v'nituach*. And then later in ויקרא *Vayikra* then we find out
how to bring an עולה olah, *Ola*. How one, we find out
that you that you flay it and you dismember it and so
on. So basically what it's saying is according to רבי עקיבא they
could have brought the עולת תמיד olat tamid. before הר סיני Har
Sinai, because or at הר סיני. Har Sinai. Again it's a little
funny before or at. A moment ago we were saying that they
were brought before הר סיני. Har Sinai. רבי עקיבא just says it
was all given at הר סיני. Har Sinai So תוספות Tosafot deals
with that problem, but let's for assuming it's going to be given
at, so more or less at the same time, somehow we could
work that out. So therefore according to רבי עקיבא if they brought
the עולת תמיד olat tamid fine, they were given all the details
around that time anyway, they knew how to bring it properly. But
according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that the details were only given
where they appear in the תורה, Torah. so the details of how
to bring a קרבן korban appear in ויקרא, so if they bring
the עולה olah before מתן תורה Mattan Torah or at the time
of מתן תורה, Mattan Torah, they're not following all the details yet,
they don't know all the details yet. So how is that possible?
Now of course the obvious question is, so how are you going
to make it better? You're going to say they're going to bring
a private עולה? olah So they also brought a private עולה olah
without doing all the details properly, because that wasn't given until later.
So also how is that possible? What's the big deal? Before the
details were given it was okay to bring it that way. What's
the big deal? So תוספות Tosafot tries to deal with this. If
you look at the little תוספות Tosafot מכדי מעיקרא לא בהפשטה michdi
me'ikara lo be'hafshata he says דוקא קמיבעיא ליה משום דעיקר הפשט כתיב
בגופיה. davka kamibaya leh mishum de'ikar hepshet ketiv begufeih.
He says because where it actually speaks about how to do the
dismembering or whatever is where the תורה Torah speaks about bringing the
עולת תמיד. olat tamid אבל מעולת ראייה אע"ג דאמת הוא דטעונה הפשט
לא קשיא ליה מידי כיון דלאו בגופיה כתיב. aval me'olat re'iah af
al gav de'emet hu deteunah hepshet lo kashya leh midi keivan delav
begufeih ketiv.
It's true all עולות olot need this, but since the תורה Torah
when it actually speaks later after הר סיני Har Sinai, about the
תמיד tamid explicitly spells out that the way the תמיד tamid, is
brought is this way, it's inconceivable that the תורה later would explicitly
say this is how you bring the תמיד, tamid not just in
general an עולה, olah and that earlier it was brought not having
been done that way. All right, so I'm not sure how persuasive
that is for us, but the גמרא Gemara feels that that's persuasive
and therefore the גמרא Gemara says it has to have been that
if the specifics of the עולת תמיד olat tamid were only given
later, that it could not be conceivable that the עולת תמיד olat
tamid was brought earlier. And therefore that עולה olah that was brought
earlier must have been a more minor עולה, olah not the most
central עולה olah, of the עולת תמיד olat tamid? with all of
its details, a more minor one of the עולת ראייה. olat re'iah.
Yes.
משה was a prophet, he knew what the הלכה halacha was going
to be.
Doesn't matter. If it wasn't commanded, it wasn't yet the הלכה. halacha.
All right anyway and besides but whether, okay I'm not even going
to I'm not going to touch that one. All right anyway okay
but so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So that's רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Ishmael, Now רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar דתניא, detanya, who's רבי אלעזר?
Rabbi Elazar? The one that says that the עולה olah must have
been a private עולה olah and not an עולת ראייה. olat re'iah.
We taught in a ברייתא. baraita. עולת תמיד העשויה בהר סיני לריח
ניחוח אשה לה'. olat tamid ha'asuyah be'Har Sinai lereyach nichoach isheh l'Hashem.
Okay
so that is a fascinating פסוק. pasuk. What does it mean העשויה
בהר סיני? ha'asuyah be'Har Sinai? Did anybody ever stop and ask themselves
what that פסוק pasuk means? We say this so often, right? But
what does it mean? Where was an עולת תמיד olat tamid. done
in הר סיני? Har Sinai. Right? So it could have just meant
an עולה olah was done in הר סיני, Har Sinai but what
does it mean העשויה בהר סיני ha'asuyah be'Har Sinai in the context
of עולת תמיד? olat tamid. So that actually on the face of
it sounds like a pretty good evidence that the עולה olah was
actually which was brought there at the foot of הר סיני. Har
Sinai, By the way, well let me just take a look here
at something. What does the רשב"ם Rashbam say? Wait, we're not done.
Okay so anyway fine. I just want to see if אפרתי Efrati
over there says anything.
Hold on. העשויה בהר סיני. ha'asuyah be'Har Sinai.
So first he says at the time of the מילואים miluim and
then he says we say מתן תורה, mattan Torah, וישם באגנות, vayasem
ba'aganot,
right?
So he says exactly what we're saying, the stuff that is at
the end of משפטים. Mishpatim? That's so anyway that's the only thing
that you find, the only עולה olah? you find mentioned in the
context of הר סיני. Har Sinai, So let's take a look. רבי
אלעזר אומר מעשיה נאמרו בסיני ועצמה לא קרבה. Rabbi Elazar omer ma'aseha
ne'emru be'Sinai ve'atzma lo karvah. Yes,
it's true at הר סיני Har Sinai we were told how to
bring an עולה, olah, but it doesn't really mean it was done
at הר סיני, Har Sinai. which is quite fascinating. It says העשויה.
ha'asuyah. It only was done later but the commandment was given at
הר סיני. Har Sinai, רבי עקיבא אומר קרבה ושוב לא פסקה. Rabbi
Akiva omer karvah veshav lo paskah. No, it was brought at הר
סיני Har Sinai. and it didn't stop after that. So they're essentially
debating what was that עולה olah. that was mentioned. And רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar really goes out of his way to interpret that עולה
olah. as not being an עולת תמיד. olat tamid אלא מה אני
מקיים הזבחים ומנחה הגשתם לי במדבר ארבעים שנה בית ישראל? ela mah
ani mekayem hazzvachim u'minchah higashtem li bamidbar arbaim shana beit Yisrael? The
פסוק pasuk that sort of says rhetorically, did you did sacrifices and
grain offerings did you bring to me in the wilderness for forty
years, oh בית ישראל, beit Yisrael, which basically the answer is no.
So what do you mean no, you didn't? Yes they did, they
brought קרבנות korbanot all forty years, they brought the תמיד tamid etc.
that started in the first year. So if you say like רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that the תמיד tamid did not start at הר
סיני, Har Sinai, then they didn't bring קרבנות korbanot for all forty
years because for the first year they didn't start bringing at least
communal sacrifices until the second year. But if you say that they
brought already the communal sacrifice of the תמיד tamid, at the foot
of הר סיני, Har Sinai, so what's this rhetorical question? You didn't
bring me sacrifices for forty years? They did! Starting at the foot
of הר סיני Har Sinai they brought the עולת תמיד. olat tamid
The גמרא Gemara says no, that's שבטו של לוי. shivto shel Levi.
That was it means you, the entire people, didn't bring it. שבט
של לוי שלא עבדו עבודה זרה הם הקריבו אותה. Shevet shel Levi
shelo avdu avoda zara heim hikrivu otah. Only the לויים Levi'im were
able to bring it, but you were disqualified because of the...
Anyway, they were disqualified anyway, they weren't כהנים. kohanim. Yeah. Okay. Anyway,
it's a funny פסוק pasuk regardless because what? You didn't bring it
for me forty years, you only brought it thirty-nine.
Anyway, very strange. Okay, but it is the point of עשייה בהר
סיני asiya behar Sinai is a strange
characterization in the עולה olah with, you know, the only thing that's
עשייה בהר סיני asiya behar Sinai is the עולה olah. and the
שלמים shelamim which is so why does it give that special status
to the עולה? olah, Okay. So so
where are we? רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar so anyway that's the two
opinions. So we have this bizarre statement by רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
that says עשייה בהר סיני asiya behar Sinai he goes out of
his way saying it wasn't on הר סיני. Har Sinai. So clearly
then it was not the תמיד, tamid, so therefore we're saying it's
an
עולת ראייה. olat re'iya. And the idea of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
that the details were only said later, so if the details were
only said later we can't conceive that the עולת תמיד olat tamid.
was done in a different way than it would later be commanded.
So it has to have been a different עולה, olah it has
to have been a private עולה. olah Okay. So those are the
three that say it was a private עולה. olah And obviously the
reverse now would be those that will say it was an עולת
התמיד. olat hatamid.
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, so הא דאמרין ha de'amrin now the other
three. בית הלל Beit Hillel that says it was a תמיד, Tamid.
that's what we said because
and that's why they feel that there's more weight to the שלמים
shelamim because only the private שלמים shelamim was done before הר סיני,
Har Sinai, the עולה olah was not a private one. רבי עקיבא
הא נמי דאמרין ha nami de'amrin and רבי עקיבא also. רבי עקיבא
says the פרטים pratim were also said at הר סיני. Har Sinai
So if the פרטים were said at הר סיני, Har Sinai, so
therefore they could have brought a regular עולה. olah At least it
was possible, all the details were given already at הר סיני, Har
Sinai so they could have brought a regular עולת תמיד olat tamid.
that could have been done with the full details. רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yose HaGelili now what about רבי יוסי הגלילי? Rabbi Yose HaGelili?
דתניא detanya because we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, actually it's both
of them are רבי עקיבא, I just realized, right? רבי עקיבא says
both things that reinforce that. First he says כללות ופרטות נאמרו בסיני,
so the details were given at הר סיני Har Sinai which allows
for it to have been the עולת תמיד. olat tamid And then
he says explicitly עולת תמיד העשויה בהר סיני olat tamid ha'asuya beHar
Sinai is the עולת תמיד. olat tamid So therefore רבי עקיבא both
of those statements reinforce that he says that it was the עולת
תמיד olat tamid. that was given that was done already at הר
סיני. Har Sinai. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר Rabbi Yose HaGelili omer and
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili says שלוש מצוות נצטוו ישראל בעלותם
לרגל. shalosh mitzvot nishtavu Yisrael be'alotam laregel. The בני ישראל were given
three מצוות mitzvot when they do עלייה לרגל. aliya laregel. ראייה, re'iya,
appearing in the מקדש Mikdash with bringing a קרבן, korban, וחגיגה, vachagiga,
the קרבן חגיגה, korban chagiga, תחוג לי, tachog li, right? Which means
celebrate which means through a קרבן. korban. ושמחה, Vesimcha, and שמחה simcha
as we have said before ושמחת בחגך vesamachta bechagecha which means eating
the meat of a קרבן. korban. יש בראייה שאין בשתיהן, Yesh bere'iya
she'ein bishteichem, there's an aspect of the קרבן ראייה korban re'iya more
demanding aspect that doesn't exist by the other two. ויש בחגיגה שאין
בשתיהן Veyesh bachagiga she'ein bishteichem and there's an aspect of the קרבן
חגיגה korban chagiga that doesn't exist by the other two. ויש בשמחה
Veyesh besimcha and there's a requirement by שמחה simcha שאין בשתיהן she'ein
bishteichem that doesn't exist by the other two. יש בראייה שאין בשתיהן
Yesh bere'iya she'ein bishteichem there's an aspect of ראייה re'iya that doesn't
is not in the other two שהרי עולה כולה לגבוה sheharei olah
kulla legavo'a because the ראייה re'iya is an עולה, olah so it's
a more it's fully given to God מה שאין בשניהם mah she'ein
bishneihem the חגיגה chagiga and the שמחה simcha are שלמים. shelamim. יש
בחגיגה מה שאין בשניהם Yesh bachagiga mah she'ein bishneihem how about the
קרבן חגיגה? korban chagiga? What's the in what way does that have
a higher something that doesn't exist in the other two? שחגיגה ישנם
לפני הדיבור מה שאין בשניהם. Shechagiga yeshnam lifnei hadibur mah she'ein bishneihem.
So there's explicitly the same argument of בית הלל. Beit Hillel. חגיגה
Chagiga existed before מתן תורה Mattan Torah and the other two, the
עולת ראייה olat re'iya and the שלמי שמחה shelamim simcha did not
exist. Again that's quite fascinating because all the תורה says is that
you had a שלמים, shelamim, right, before over there to say oh
look it's a שלמי חגיגה shalmei chagiga but it wasn't a שלמי
שמחה. shalmei simcha. I mean again what allows us to define that
as a שלמי חגיגה shalmei chagiga and it couldn't have been a
שלמי שמחה? shalmei simcha? You know I really don't know. But anyway
but in clearly at least by the עולה olah. he's denying that
that was an עולת ראייה olat re'iya and he's making it therefore
implicitly since that seems to be our only two choices here עולת
ראייה olat re'iya or עולת תמיד olas tamid, therefore implicitly saying it
was an עולת תמיד.
olas tamid We have a whole מחלוקת Machloket could it have been
an עולה olah before? Like what they did for generations?
You mean the עולה olah, what makes it an עולת ראייה? olat
re'iya? Right, at least the עולת ראייה olat re'iya fits because as
רש"י Rashi says ויחזו את האלהים, vayichezu et ha'Elohim, you know.
יש בשמחה מה שאין בשניהם Yesh besimcha mah she'ein bishneihem now שמחה
simcha has something that doesn't apply in the other two. שהשמחה נוהגת
באנשים ובנשים Shehasimcha noheget banashim uvanashim men and women are obligated in
this in the קרבן
שמחה korban simcha מה שאין בשניהם mah she'ein bishneihem which is not
true about the עולת ראייה olat re'iya and the שלמי חגיגה. shalmei
chagiga. Okay so now you see it's clear that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Ishmael's holds that it was not the עולה olah beforehand was not
an עולת ראייה olat re'iya like בית הלל. Beit Hillel. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ורבי ישמעאל מאי טעמא כמוקים לה
כבית שמאי VeRabbi Yishmael mai ta'ama kemokim lah keBeit Shammai now why
so now fine that's the lineup. Now we're going to question the
lineup. Three against three but we're going to try to win over
one of the votes. So רבי ישמעאל we said was going like
בית שמאי Beit Shammai because רבי ישמעאל says that only the כללים
klalim were said at הר סיני, Har Sinai, the details were only
said when they were spelled out. out later on and therefore we
figured that he couldn't have held that the עולה olah was brought
earlier without having known those details. So why do we say he
was like בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? אי סלקא דעתך עולה שקרבו במדבר
עולת תמיד הוי ei salka deitach olah shekeribu bamidbar olas tamid havaei
because if he were to have held that that עולה olah at
הר סיני Har Sinai, was an עולת תמיד, olas tamid so and
he also holds that the details were only spelled out when they
were spelled out, so מיכא מידי דמעיקרא לא בעי הפשט וניתוח ולבסוף
בעי הפשט וניתוח mi’ka meedi d’mei’ikara lo baei hafshat u’nituach u’levasof baei
hafshat u’nituach it couldn't have been that they brought an עולת תמיד
olas tamid. that in the end would have required all of those
details of flaying and dismembering and initially was brought without that being
followed? Again, that's particularly a challenge by the עולת תמיד olas tamid.
more than it would have been by a private עולה. olah So
that's how we argued implicitly that that could not have been an
עולת תמיד. olas tamid Gemara says, but one minute, maybe that's not
right. Maybe he could have allowed that it was brought in a
different way. And I'll show you. והא רבי יוסי הגלילי דאמר עולה
שקרבו במדבר עולת תמיד הוי. v’ha Rabbi Yose HaGlili d’amar olah shekeribu
bamidbar olas tamid havaei. We just quoted רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGlili that says that the עולה olah brought beforehand was not a
private עולה, olah right? The only thing that existed before the דיבור
dibbur was the שלמי חגיגה. shalmei chagigah. So the עולה olah brought
beforehand was an עולת תמיד. olas tamid, That was implicit in רבי
יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGlili. And he also holds מעיקרא לא בעי
הפשט וניתוח ולבסוף בעי הפשט וניתוח. mei’ikara lo baei hafshat u’nituach u’levasof
baei hafshat u’nituach. And he actually holds that yes, the way the
עולת תמיד olas tamid, was brought changed. Before מתן תורה Mattan Torah
it did not have or you know before the details were given
it did not have, it was not flayed and dismembered and afterward
it was. דתניא, D’tanya, here we have a ברייתא. braita. רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer. He says explicitly both of these
points. עולה שקרבו במדבר אינה טעונה הפשט וניתוח. Olah shekeribu bamidbar einah
te’unah hafshat u’nituach.
The עולה Olah, that they brought in the wilderness, right, presumably at
the foot of הר סיני, Har Sinai, that was the עולת תמיד,
olas tamid, did not require flaying and dismembering. לפי שאין הפשט וניתוח
אלא מאהל מועד ואילך. lefi she’ein hafshat u’nituach ela mei’ohel mo’ed v’eilach.
Because those details were only given starting at אהל מועד. So here
you have a position that's explicitly like רבי ישמעאל, that the details
were given at אהל מועד and the way it was brought changed
starting at אהל מועד and still can accept that when it was
brought at the foot of הר סיני and that it was even
if it was an עולת תמיד, olas tamid, even if it was
a communal עולת תמיד, olas tamid, it still did not have those
details that it would later have. So you see it's possible to
hold that the way it was brought changed. Gemara says, you know
what, you're right. תמי מכאן רבי ישמעאל. Tami mikaan Rabbi Ishmael. So
fine, cross רבי ישמעאל off the בית שמאי Beis Shammai list and
move him to the בית הלל Beis Hillel list, which is okay
because we're going to wind up, you know, we like בית הלל
Beis Hillel anyway and we're going to rule like בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. Okay, so that was a long and pretty complicated discussion again
about, but what's fascinating is trying to find a forerunner
to עולת ראיה ושלמי חגיגה. olas re’iyah u’shalmei chagigah. And to me
anyway, although, you know, in the end this winds up being the
position of בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, there's a certain power of seeing
the idea of, you know, because that פסוקים psukim, there at the
foot of הר סיני are very like explicit, very anthropomorphic and very
explicit, right, ויחזו את האלוהים, v’yechezu es HaElokim, you know, you know,
ותחת רגליו כמעשה לבנת הספיר. v’tachas raglav k’maaseh livnas hasapir. And so
therefore identifying that the עולה Olah that's being brought in that context
as an עולת ראיה, olas re’iyah, you know, to me that's like
bringing a very like powerful imagery into that whole experience of what
it means to do ראיה re’iyah and to appear in the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But in the end that's only according to בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. According to בית הלל Beis Hillel the significance of
that עולה Olah is put aside and that becomes the עולת תמיד,
Olat Tamid which says something interesting also about that experience about the
idea of the עולת תמיד, Olat Tamid, right? Sort of, you know,
sort of holding those two things up to one another are also
an interesting type of comparison. On the one hand you have that
unique experience three times in the year at the sort of private
level, that direct encountering with God, the עולת ראיה, olas re’iyah, and
then you have the idea of that sort of very daily service,
which is represented, which is not a big, you know, religious metaphysical
high, just every single day, you know, you bring an עולה Olah
in the morning and an עולה Olah. in the afternoon and that
sense of like that regularity of service, you know, and sort of
which one of those two are we going to highlight sort of
occurred here at the foot of הר סיני. So on the one
hand the בית שמאי Beis Shammai approach, you know, I think it
brings a powerful imagery to what we think about in terms of
the עולת ראיה, olas re’iyah, whereas you can also understand, you know,
a בית הלל Beis Hillel approach maybe is trying to give a
little bit more of the weight on what that sort of daily
service means when you don't have those sort of, you know, intense
moments. So that's I think a fascinating question of how to frame
it. I don't know what to do with the issue of why
we can assume that the שלמים shlamim is a שלמי חגיגה shalmei
chagigah rather than let's say a שלמי שמחה. shalmei simchah. שמחה Simchah
to me would have been a better sort of link. But nevertheless,
in the end it's just different ways of getting to this issue
of whether you have a higher minimum for the עולה Olah... or
a higher minimum for the שלמי חגיגה. shalmei chagigah. And again, this
very famous and debate of רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא Rabbi Ishmael v’Rabbi
Akiva of whether the details were given later, which is the פשט
pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, which is sort of רבי ישמעאל's general
approach to go by the פשט of the פסוקים, pesukim or רבי
עקיבא that says all the details were given at הר סיני, which
again, I think you could read that not to mean that the
details necessarily were spelled out at הר סיני, but they were implicitly
given at הר סיני, which is sort of רבי עקיבא's general hermeneutics
in general. Yes.
What was our פסוק pasuk that you said was explicit about flaying
and dismembering?
Yeah, I think it's just because the עולה, Olah, yeah that's a
good question. I think it's because the beginning of צו, Tzav, it
just said the עולה Olah.
without saying which עולה Olah it is.
Yeah, but the חז״ל Chazal understood that היא העולה Hi ha'olah means
the עולת תמיד Tamid, because, yeah, it's because the פסוקים that you
need הפסוק ניחוח Hapasuk Nichuach is in צו, Tzav, right? The beginning
of צו, Tzav, right? היא העולה על מוקדה על המזבח כל הלילה.
Hi ha'olah al mokda al hamizbeach kol halayla. Right. Actually that doesn't
say...
that doesn't say the הפסוק ניחוח. Hapasuk Nichuach. הפסוק ניחוח Hapasuk Nichuach
is the עולה Olah in ויקרא א׳ Vayikra Alef and that's a
private עולה.
Olah Right.
Right.
The עולה... Olah
because היא העולה Hi ha'olah in the beginning of צו, Tzav, חז״ל
Chazal understand to be the תמיד. Tamid.
Yeah, but you're right, הפסוק ניחוח Hapasuk Nichuach in ויקרא א׳ Vayikra
Alef is about the private עולה, olah. right? אם עולה קרבנו, Im
olah korbano, right? אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן. Adam ki yakriv mikem
korban.
Yeah. I'm not exactly sure what תוספות Tosafot was referring to there
about why דווקא davka by זה ze by זה. ze. What? Yeah,
I don't know. You could check some מהרש״א Maharsha or whatever, I
didn't get a chance. But I don't know, it's a good point
why תוספות Tosafot says it says explicitly by that.
Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. איבעיא להו לרב
חסדא. Ibaiah lehu leRav Chisda. Okay, so now רב חסדא Rav Chisda
asks: האי קרא היכי כתיב? Hai kra heichi ktiv?
How do you read the verse that we've been talking about here
at the end of משפטים? וישלח את נערי בני ישראל ויעלו עולות.
Vayishlach et na'arei bnei Yisrael vaya'alu olot.
He sent the young men of Israel and they brought burnt
offerings. כבשים. Kevasim. What would those עולות olot be? Maybe sheep? Or
we don't know what they would be, but let's assume sheep because
that would be like a standard עולה. olah. And then, but meaning
there's a period after the word עולות. olot. They brought עולות. olot.
כבשים Kevasim was not mentioned.
Whatever, right. But meaning whatever those עולות olot were, maybe they were
כבשים, kevasim, who knows what they were, but it's in order to
make a contrast. Period. If you have the word period, he would
have said that, ויעלו עולות vaya'alu olot period, ויזבחו זבחים שלמים לה׳
פרים, vayizbechu zvachim shlamim l'Hashem parim,
and then they brought the sacrifices שלמים shlamim as cows. So meaning
the cows is only going on the שלמים, shlamim, the עולה olah.
we don't know what it is, there was a period after עולות.
olot. Is that how you read it? או דילמא, O dilma, or
do you read it, אידי ואידי פרים הוו? idi v'idi parim havu?
No, פרים parim goes on everything. ויעלו עולות ויזבחו זבחים שלמים לה׳
Vaya'alu olot vayizbechu zvachim shlamim l'Hashem
and all of that was פרים, parim, all of these, the עולה
and the שלמים shlamim were all cows. So the גמרא Gemara says,
למאי נפקא מינה? lemai nafka mina? What do I care? Like it
was all past history, what difference does it make?
Does the debate...
and it could
have been a תמיד, it
could have been a פר. par. That's a good point actually. The
גמרא Gemara could say the נפקא מינה nafka mina would be whether
it allows for the idea that the עולה was a
תמיד. It's a very
good point. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. מר זוטרא אמר לפיסוק טעמים. Mar Zutra amar lepisuk
teamim.
In order to know how to read the טראפ. trop. Do you
read לה׳, l'Hashem, do you read ויעלו עולות vaya'alu olot and read
with an אתנחתא etnachtah which is essentially a period, or do you
read it with a type of a טראפ trop that pauses but
isn't a period and allows פרים parim to go back on both?
Okay. So, לפיסוק טעמים. lepisuk teamim. רב אחא בריה דרבא אמר לאומר
הרי עלי עולה כעולה שקרבו במדבר מאי.
Rav Acha brei d'Rava amar l'omer
harei alai olah k'olah shekarvu bamidbar mai.
If somebody took a vow: I obligate myself to bring an עולה
just like the one brought in the wilderness. פרים הוו או כבשים
הוו? Parim havu o kevasim havu? Would it be cows or would
it be sheep? Which is again interesting because even if you put
the period, you don't know that it was sheep. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't know. But Michael makes an excellent
point that if you read that it was the עולת תמיד, it
had to be כבשים. kevasim. Okay. Unless you say that the פרטים
weren't said, so it could have also been a cow beforehand. I
don't know how much you say that the פרטים weren't said. All
right, that's the end of that debate. Now we get to, I
mean connected, but we now introduce a new aspect of this whole
discussion of what is the minimum on the קרבנות. korbanot. Let's take
a look. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. We taught over there, first משנה,
mishna, פאה, Peah, which we say in דאוון. daven. אלו דברים שאין
להם שיעור. Elu devarim she'ein lahem shiur. The following things have no
minimum. הפאה והביכורים והראיון
וגמילות חסדים. Hapeah vehabikkurim vehara'ayon ugmilut chasadim. פאה, Peah, okay, which is
the corner of the field; ביכורים, bikkurim, which we just read in
the תורה, right, you go and you sort of see the first
fruit and you bring them; ראיון, ra'ayon, which is an interesting word
but it means ראיה, reiah, why it says ראיון ra'ayon we'll talk
about, okay, but that's what we're talking about, the מצוה mitzvah of
ראיה; reiah; וגמילות חסדים ותלמוד תורה, ugmilut chasadim vetalmud Torah, and the
learning of תורה.
Now by the way, there are, okay, so let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבי יוחנן כסבורים אנו לומר,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan kasvurim anu lomar, we thought to say, שהראיון אין
לו שיעור למעלה אבל יש לו שיעור למטה. shehara'ayon ein lo shiur
lema'la aval yesh lo shiur lemata. That these things don't have a
maximum but they do have a minimum. Now this is an interesting
question, just to say briefly what the issues are around it. So
what does it mean that these don't have a שיעור, shiur, they
don't have a limit? So does it mean they don't have an
upper limit or they don't have a lower limit or either? So
actually it's not so clear. פאה Peah certainly has to have a
lower, I mean,
פאה Peah doesn't have a lower limit, you can give even let's
say the smallest amount. ביכורים... Bikkurim... what? It doesn't, excuse me. It
doesn't have a lower limit, you can give even the smallest amount.
Same by ביכורים. bikkurim. But do they have an upper limit? Yes.
Michael says you have to. Why do you have to?
You can't make the whole field פאה.
Peah. So actually, right, so that's actually... it has a whole discussion
in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* it might be possible to give your whole
field as פאה *Pe'ah*. The ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* says one minute then it's
not a corner. So the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* says no it's not something,
פאה *Pe'ah* means in contrast to something else. The ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* says
no you're not obligated in פאה *Pe'ah* until you cut the first
stalk because it says בקצרכם *Bekutzrechem*. So it says after you've cut
the first stalk, one stalk could be what you are taking and
the rest, 99.9% could be פאה *Pe'ah*. So that actually is theoretically
possible, but there are other opinions that say that's not true, that
פאה *Pe'ah* at most could be half, it can't be any more
than half, similar discussion about about what? It's still a limit, right.
So some say that when it says it doesn't have a limit
it means it doesn't have a lower limit. It's debated whether it
has an upper limit. Okay, but some say no, it doesn't have
an upper limit. As soon as you become obligated everything, all the
rest, could be considered פאה *Pe'ah*. Same type of a question about
ביכורים *Bikkurim*.
Give your whole tree as the first fruits, right?
Yeah, but the let me take a look at תוספות *Tosafot*. He
brings down a similar discussion about ביכורים *Bikkurim*.
Yeah, there's the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan עושה אדם כל
שדהו ביכורים *Rabbi Yochanan Oseh Adam Kol Sadehu Bikkurim*. So what? Your
first fruit?
I
mean you would
think, right,
yeah, you mean because it's first relative to others. Yeah.
Well,
yeah, I don't know, I'd have to I'd have to see that
one ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* but there actually is an opinion which is very
surprising. Again, you would have thought it might mean a lower limit
but actually, but when we say things like גמילות חסדים *Gemilut Chasadim*
and תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah* also we're saying that there's you know,
right, right. Anyway so that is the question, so פאה *Pe'ah* and
ביכורים *Bikkurim* are we just saying no lower limit or are we
also saying no upper limit and there's going to be a similar
type of a discussion by ראיון *Re'ayon*, yes.
פאה *Pe'ah* and ביכורים *Bikkurim* both have rabbinically prescribed,
right, that is true, and then there is some discussion in that
same ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* about whether those rabbinic minimums are also, whether this
is talking just about biblical minimums or whether those minimums might be,
are they only rabbinic, are they biblical? So there's a whole question
here whether we're talking about are there lower limits or are there
upper limits? Are there no lower limits or no upper limits or
neither? So now let's sort of see how that's spelled out in
terms of the what do you call it in terms of the
מצוה mitzvah *Mitzvah* of ראייה re'iyah *Re'iyah*. אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
נצטוונו לומר הראיון אין לו שיעור ein lo shiur, למעלה *Amar Rabbi
Yochanan Nitztavnu Lumar HaRe'ayon Ein Lo Shiur Lema'alah*. There's no upper limit,
meaning you can bring as many, spend as much money on your
קרבנות korbanot, *Korbanot* as you want. אבל יש לו שיעור למטה *Aval
Yesh Lo Shiur Lemata*. There is a lower limit. And again by
the way if you were to apply that to the rest of
the משנה *Mishnah* it would say the same by פאה *Pe'ah* and
ביכורים *Bikkurim* that there might be you know no upper limit but
yes a lower limit. You know so you could read it in
you know the exact flip of what we were saying. Anyway that's
what we assumed, that there was no upper limit but there was
a lower limit. עד שבא רבי אושעיה ברבי ולימד *Ad Sheba Rabbi
Oshaia B'Rabbi Velimmed*, until Rabbi Oshaia the son of Rabbi, not the
son of Rabbi, the great Rabbi Oshaia came and taught, הראיון אין
לו שיעור ein lo shiur לא למעלה ולא למטה *HaRe'ayon Ein Lo
Shiur Lo Lema'alah V'lo Lemata*. There's no lower limit and there's no
upper limit. So you can spend as little as you want and
as much as you want. So okay, because again we're talking about
דאורייתא *De'oraita* versus דרבנן *Derabbanan*. אבל חכמים אומרים *Aval Chachamim Omerim*, but
the Sages say, הראייה מעה כסף החגיגה שתי כסף *HaRe'iyah Ma'ah Kesef
HaChagigah Shtei Kesef*. Okay now
so now the question is this read this way, אבל חכמים אומרים
*Aval Chachamim Omerim*, right, sounds like that's a position that argues on
רבי אושעיה *Rabbi Oshaia*. He says there's no limit, but the חכמים
*Chachamim* say there is a limit. But that's probably not פשט *Pshat*
and you look at the אלבק *Albeck* and he makes it clear.
He says אבל אמרו חכמים הראייה מעה כסף *Aval Amru Chachamim HaRe'iyah
Ma'ah Kesef*, meaning Rabbi Oshaia is saying biblically there's no lower limit
but rabbinically there is a lower limit, okay? So you can spend
as much on your קרבנות korbanot *Korbanot* as you want and you
can spend as little as you want biblically, but rabbinically there is
a lower limit. And again that goes to what Charlie just said
about פאה *Pe'ah* and ביכורים *Bikkurim*. Biblically could be there's no lower
limit, could be rabbinically there's a lower limit, but biblically there is
not. So here he's reading that by at least ראייה re'iyah *Re'iyah*
this משנה *Mishnah* should be read to be talking biblically. We're putting
aside rabbinic limits separately and neither a lower limit nor an upper
limit. You can spend as little as you want, as much as
you want, but the rabbis gave a minimum. Okay and that presumably
would be a similar way to read things like the פאה *Pe'ah*
and the ביכורים *Bikkurim* as well. Okay so that's what so that's
point number one. Now, מאי הראיון *Mai HaRe'ayon*? Now why do you
say this word ראיון *Re'ayon* instead of ראייה re'iyah *Re'iyah*? What's that
supposed to mean? So רבי יוחנן אומר ראיית פנים בעזרה *Rabbi Yochanan
Omer Re'iyat Panim Ba'azarah*. It means appearing in the בית המקדש Beis
Ha-Mikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. ריש לקיש אמר ראיית פנים בקרבן Reish Lakish amar
re'iyat panim be-korban, *Resh Lakish Amar Re'iyat Panim Bekorban*, bringing a קרבן
korban. *Korban*. Now that's very terse you know and a little bit
unclear so what exactly are they talking about?
So תוספות *Tosafot* brings in a whole interesting ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* but first
we'll deal with what the בבלי *Bavli* seems to be saying. So
it seems to be saying that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is saying
that you want to appear a million times in the בית המקדש
Mikdash. *Beit HaMikdash* געזונטערהייט gesunterheit. *Gezunterheit* but maybe you cannot bring, now
we're sort of shifting from this idea of how much money you're
spending on a קרבן korban *Korban* to number of kinds. So you
can appear many times, there's no limit to how many times you
appear, but maybe there's a limit to how many קרבנות *Korbanot* you
bring. And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Resh Lakish* is saying there's also
no limit to how many קרבנות *Korbanot* you bring. So let's see
how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* unpacks.
Well, let's take a look. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara
unpacks this: דעיקר
הרגל כולי עלמא לא פליגי דראיית פנים בקרבן. de'ikar ha-regel kuli alma
lo peligi de-re'iyat panim be-korban. When you're talking about יום טוב Yom
Tov itself, nobody disagrees that there is a, that we're talking about
about bringing the קרבן. korban. What does that mean? So take a
look at רשי, Rashi, he says, let me find the רשי. Rashi.
So רשי Rashi says by ריש לקיש Reish Lakish ראיית פנים בקרבן,
re'iyat panim be-korban, so he says וצריך להביא קרבן על כל פעם
ופעם, vetsarich le-havi korban al kol pa'am va-pa'am, so that what ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish, is saying is, is that every time you appear,
not only are you allowed to bring multiple קרבנות, but you have
to bring a קרבן korban every time that you appear. So
if you come multiple times, he says like this, since the תורה
says three times in the, three times you should appear before me,
ולא יראו פני ריקם, velo yeira'u panai reikam, do not come empty-handed,
that means whenever you appear on the first day יום טוב, Yom
Tov, the prohibition of do not appear empty-handed applies. So according to
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish there is no minimum, doesn't just mean you're
allowed to do as much as you want, but it means that
if you appear multiple times you must every single time bring a
קרבן. korban Now again that's not the normal sense you have by
a phrase אין לו שיעור, ein lo shiur. right, knows אין לו
שיעור sort of gives you latitude, this is making a demand, but
this is at least the way that רשי Rashi is reading it,
which means that according to רבי יוחנן you bring your קרבן korban.
once and then you can appear multiple times with, you know, do
whatever you want, appear many times or not, whereas ריש לקיש is
saying no, every single time you appear you have to bring a
קרבן korban with you, the first day. Well take a look, okay,
כי פליגי בשאר ימי הרגל, ki peligi bish'ar yemei ha-regel, so the
first day it's saying nobody disagreed actually, even רבי יוחנן would say
that on the first day where the תורה says ולא יראו פני
ריקם, velo yeira'u panai reikam, every time you appear you have to
be bringing your קרבן. korban What's the debate? On the rest of
יום טוב. Yom Tov. כל
היכא דאתי ואייתי כולי עלמא לא פליגי דמקבלינן מיניה, kol heicha de-atei
ve-ayeiti kuli alma lo peligi de-mekablin minei,
nobody disagrees that you're allowed to, again, which is the normal sense
of אין לו שיעור. So everybody agrees you can come as many
times as you want, and if you want to bring a קרבן
korban, every single time, געזונטערהייט. כי פליגי דאתי ולא אייתי, ki peligi
de-atei ve-lo ayeiti, the debate is you came to the בית המקדש
Mikdash without a קרבן korban, in your hand on another day of
יום טוב. Yom Tov. רבי יוחנן סבר ראיית פנים בעזרה, Rabbi Yochanan
savar re'iyat panim ba-azarah, that no, there's no limit to how many
times you want to come with or without a קרבן, korban, וכל
אימת דאתי לא צריך לאתויי, ve-chol eimas de-atei lo tsarich le-atoye, whenever
you want to come, come, don't need to bring a קרבן, korban,
no gift is needed. ריש לקיש אמר ראיית פנים בקרבן, no, every
time you appear it's appearing means with a קרבן, korban, דכל אימת
דאתי צריך לאתויי, de-chol eimas de-atei tsarich le-atoye, every time you come
you have to bring. So this is quite fascinating and now, and
this is important right because it gets to the way in which
we've been framing that we said the מצוה mitzvah of ראייה re'iyah
is the מצוה mitzvah to bring a קרבן, korban but it's not
really the מצוה mitzvah to bring a קרבן, korban the מצוה mitzvah
is really to appear in the המקדש. I asked you the other
day what would happen if somebody didn't appear in the המקדש and
sent a קרבן korban to be brought for him, would they be
like יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of קרבן korban, without being יוצא
yotzei the מצוה of ראייה in the עזרה, azarah, right, but these
are two things that are very intertwined.
So now the גמרא is saying how about having not קרבן korban?
without ראייה but ראייה without קרבן, korban. appearing without a קרבן? korban
And it says ולא יראו פני ריקם, velo yeira'u panai reikam, so
what the גמרא in the first framing is saying is that according
to everybody the first day where it's like a demand performance, you've
got to be there, right, if every time you come multiple times
that day, each time coming means bringing a קרבן. korban? But the
debate is on the rest of יום טוב. Yom Tov. Is it
possible to appear during יום טוב Yom Tov without a קרבן korban
or does appearing always mean appearing with a קרבן? korban, Okay, that
would not, okay, so that's one version of the מחלוקת machloket we'll
have another version later. Let's at least read one proof to it
and then we'll wrap up for today. So איתיביה ריש לקיש לרבי
יוחנן ולא יראו פני ריקם,
eisivei Reish Lakish le-Rabbi Yochanan
velo yeira'u panai reikam, you can't come empty-handed, so how can you
let this guy come empty-handed on חול המועד? Chol Ha-Moed? So אמר
ליה בעיקר הרגל, amar lei be-ikar ha-regel, that was the first day
יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Okay, איתיביה, eisivei, another example, ולא יראו פני ריקם velo yeira'u panai
reikam בזבחים, bizevachim, with קרבנות you have to bring it. אתם מזבחים
או אינו אלא בעופות ומנחות? atam mizvachim o eino ela be-ofot u-minachot?
Maybe you can bring a like bird or grain offerings? That's also
coming with something in your hand. דינו ואומר dinu ve-omeir a logical
derivation. נאמר חגיגה להדיוט ונאמר ראייה לגבוה. ne'emar chagigah le-hediot ve-ne'emar re'iyah
la-gavo'ah. When you bring the חגיגה, chagigah, right, you bring it then
it's something that so we'll see in a minute that a חגיגה
chagigah that you bring has to be something that's a real animal.
So not, real animal, whatever, a mammal, not a bird or things.
And now that's one of your obligations and your other obligations is
appearing before God. מה חגיגה האמורה להדיוט זבחים אף ראייה האמורה לגבוה
זבחים. ma chagigah ha-amurah le-hediot zevachim af re'iyah ha-amurah la-gavo'ah zevachim. And
how do you know by the way a חגיגה chagigah is a
sheep or cow? Because it says ולא ילין חלב חגיג עד בוקר,
velo yalin cheilev chagig ad boker, another פסוק. pasuk. So if a
חגיגה chagigah has fat, it's not a bird, it's either a sheep
or a cow. So therefore the Maybe the ראיה re'iah has to
be a sheep or a calf. Now,
זבחים. zvachim. מה הן זבחים? ma hen zvachim? Now what are these
sacrifices? עולות. olot. How do you know? אתה אומר עולות או אינו
אלא שלמים? atah omer olot o eino ela shlamim? Maybe the ראיה
re'iah has to be brought as a שלמים? shlamim? נדמו. nidmu. נאמר
חגיגה להדיוט ונאמר ראיה לגבוה. ne'emar chagiga l'hedyot v'ne'emar re'iah l'gavoah. No,
we can make a logical derivation. You bring a חגיגה chagiga and
you bring a
ראיה re'iah to God. מה חגיגה האמורה להדיוט ראוי לו? ma chagiga
ha'emura l'hedyot ra'uy lo? When you bring your חגיגה, chagiga, you're celebrating,
so you benefit from it. It's a שלמים, shlamim, you can eat
from it. אף ראיה האמורה לגבוה ראוי לו? af re'iah ha'emura l'gavoah
ra'uy lo? When you appear before God and you're giving it to
God, ראוי לו, ra'uy lo, something that's all for God, something that's
an עולה. Okay, וכן בדין, v'chein b'din, and anyway that makes sense
that God should get an עולה. שלא יהא שולחנך מלא ושולחן רבך
ריקן. shelo yehei shulchancha malei v'shulchan rabacha reikan. Using very anthropomorphic, right,
imagery? You're to, I know, your table shouldn't be full, you get
all the meat of the חגיגה chagiga and God doesn't get any
meat, so God should get the עולה. Anyway, there's a whole long
point to say, look, you've got to bring a קרבן korban. when
you appear. And the obvious answer is, אמר ליה בעיקר הרגל. amar
lei b'ikar ha'regel. Okay, on first day יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
anyway, so we'll end with that for now. But again, it's very
important, right, that it's being framed here as not as a חיוב
chiyuv of קרבן, korban, but a חיוב chiyuv that when you appear,
לא יראו פני ריקם lo yeira'u panai reikam demands that that appearing
be accompanied with a קרבן. korban? And therefore it raises the question,
is it possible to come after the קרבן, korban, to come again
without the קרבן? korban And here we have everybody saying that on
the first day, every time you bring the קרבן, korban? and the
question is later days. So we'll see different framing later. But again,
it's the interesting flip question to think about is, if you sent
a קרבן korban, without coming, would that mean anything? Or is it
always the combination of the coming with the קרבן? Okay, we'll end
here for now.
Why wouldn't we also meet on a random Thursday? What? I mean
if it's just a random Thursday, you don't bring a קרבן, right?
Right, yeah. It's not part of the רגל. regel. Yeah, exactly. Why
would somebody come without...